# Joel Worrall

20 Hamlet Circle, Mechanicsburg, PA 17050 - joel@joelworrall.com - 717.385.9970

Executive Management, Strategic Leadership, Innovation, Brand Development, Technology Business and Product Development, Leveraging Information Technology in Business Transformation

## **Summary**

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. Ten years ago, I began the journey of growing my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership and transformation, strategic planning and execution, brand building, board engagement, and understanding the true value of servant leadership.

Today, my experiences have equipped me with a team-oriented management philosophy and strategic management experience at various levels and in numerous settings. My goal is to invest my skills and history in the digital world as well as my management background in both the software and international nonprofit sectors to provide senior executive leadership to an organization with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, an executive team I can pour into, and a vision I can help guide.

## Education

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA Master of Arts in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA

## Experience

- Corporate strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- A history of achieving improbable results under radical resource constraints
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Organizational management of departments across distributed offices and continents
- Fundraising experience at the mass-marketing and multi-million dollar levels, including proposal creation and presentation
- Brand development and messaging
- A commitment to thoughtful innovation as the lifeblood of any vibrant organization
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- A ten-year history of providing direction and oversight outside of my academic disciplines
- 8 years of board reporting experience and engagement
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Strong presentation and written communication skills
- Conference and public speaking experience
- Teaching skills, authoring and presenting compelling content
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Cultivating a teachable spirit and a commitment to lifelong learning
- A deep loyalty to organizations I serve as well as the people who serve the organization

- Vendor and consulting selection and management across a number of disciplines
- Significant consulting, customer facing, and relationship management experience
- Outsourced workforce management experience: offshore and remote
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including providing product and marketing direction to a successful open source software project

## **Employment History**

### CURE International / PA and International / October 2009 to Present

<u>Chief Technology Officer and Interim Executive Leadership</u> – June 2016 - present <u>Chief Technology Officer</u> (marketing and technology departments) – May 2014 to present <u>Vice President of Technology and Marketing</u> – July 2010 to May 2014 <u>Vice President of Technology</u> – October 2009 to July 2010

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Established the brand and messaging of CURE International
- Authored and led the messaging, content, and execution for CURE's largest annual fundraising event
- Member of the executive leadership team providing oversight, strategic direction, and board-level reporting responsibilities to a global nonprofit healthcare organization with 1,500 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries
- Championed the use of the StratOp strategic management process in corporate-wide and department-level strategic planning and execution
- Managed a budget of over \$4M encompassing technology and fundraising needs
- Represented the leadership of CURE and its mission to partners and donors
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations during the 2014 attack on CURE's hospital in Kabul, Afghanistan as well as the unexpected transition of a CEO in 2016
- Authored significant content on behalf of executive management, CEO, and Board
- Invested in culture-building activities, including exercises skills as a teacher and presenter in the organization's weekly devotional / staff meeting
- Served through the transition of two CEO's, four executive changes in field operational leadership, and one founder transition
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program
- Directed the creation of CURE's radio content marketing strategy, reaching a weekly, targeted audience of nearly 2 million at a fraction of traditional marketing strategy costs
- Initiated partnership programs with music artists, churches, campuses, and businesses
- Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
- Built and launched the award-winning cure.org
- Established CURE as a world leader in the movement for nonprofits to use open source tools for communications, fundraising, and operational systems
- Co-founded the award-winning <u>CUREkids</u> platform and operationalized the program across a global network of healthcare facilities
- Co-founded the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source software project, creating a modern software platform for charitable hospitals in the developing world

 As of July 2016, provided interim, executive oversight to CURE through a CEO transition as part of a three-person leadership team

## joelworrall.com personal consulting / periodically October 2009 - present

#### Sample 1: Early-stage product startup, serving as consultative CTO

- Provided product focus, technology selection, and branding direction
- Identified and recruited technology, marketing, and design talent to produce a product and a brand worthy of a national launch
- Guided brand direction, marketing and PR opportunities, and charitable aims of the corporation
- Supported the initial fundraising for the company with strategic and technical direction

#### Sample 2: Business model transformation and product due diligence

- Evaluated the business model of a national company focused on delivering rental services in entertainment settings, looking to transition to a modern, Internet business model
- Recommended and reviewed appropriate technology choices, architectures, and business processes
- Provided 1-year review and reporting to the board of directors on progress towards expected outcomes and goals

## Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. / MA & PA / July 2006 to October 2009

<u>Vice President, Engineering & Development</u> – March 2009 to October 2009

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

Development Manager – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

- Responsible for technology roadmap, partner selection, R&D, and all engineering staffing (FTE, contract, partner, and outsourcing) for a 40-person department
- Led architecture and delivery of merged company's first product release
- Provided technical and thought leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete SaaS multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Guided the engineering organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of offshore, outsourced team
- Earned five separate promotions over a 3-year period, simultaneously managing teams and projects in Pennsylvania and Boston offices, including necessary business travel
- Charged with the release planning and execution for two different SaaS platforms in two different technology stacks, combining team members from both offices as well as offshore, outsourced resources
- Integrating learning platform with social media platform to deliver Social Learning Suite
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Developed and managing corporate outsourcing strategy with offshore outsourcing partner to provide variable staffing and focus engineering resources on innovation
- Performed technical diligence in acquisition of the Prospero Social Media platform
- Implemented lightweight, effective performance review and project scheduling
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships
- Coordinated department-wide training in vendor-specific technologies

## Java Brewery, Inc / Pennsylvania

Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant – April 2003 to June 2006

- Engaged in outsourced product development, management, strategic partnerships, technology, product, and market research, and executive leadership
- Provided recruiting services, partnerships, and product due diligence
- Served as technical liaison and interim managing engineer for multiple organizations seeking to build development teams, conducting training, recruitment, and technical specification assistance
- Analysis of company models, performing architecture, requirements, design and implementation services
- Architected the content management tools for (at the time) the 8th most trafficked property on the Internet, comcast.net

### CommNav, Inc / Pennsylvania / July 2000 to April 2003

Lead Architect – July 2000 to April 2003

- Responsible for approving designs and documentation, overseeing and mentoring junior developers, and managing testing for all next-generation product development efforts
- Architected, designed, and led development of the CommNav portal infrastructure and related business productivity applications
- Primary author of the development API's and system documentation

### Personal

Since 2007, I've been married to my best friend, Cre Carbonaro-Worrall. We have two two girls, Eliana (born 2011) and Adalie (born 2012). The three of them amount to my favorite people I've ever had the privilege of knowing. I'm the first of six children to a small-town country pastor and his wife. I'm a 2nd generation American whose family came from England in the late 40's, and the first member of my immediate family to either graduate from college or receive a postgraduate degree.

I've spent my life learning what it means to be a friend, and I've spent most of my career trying to be the kind of supervisor and leader for whom I'd want to I work. My Christian faith is the absolute core of who I am. Because of both upbringing and experience, I believe that doing God's work in the world by investing time, talent, and treasure is the greatest calling and gift any of us can be offered; and though I don't believe that vocational ministry is the pinnacle of service, I am intensely grateful for the opportunities I've had to apply my gifts born out of years in the marketplace to missional and charitable outcomes.

## **Interests**

International travel, information technology in the developing world, the Ancient Near East, Biblical studies, academic writing, teaching, U2, the Cleveland Browns, offline first design, modern technology business models, exposing children (especially females and underrepresented demographics) to programming and science concepts, digital transformation in healthcare